Almost starting. Set up.
All right. בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, live from this beautiful spring day
in New York. We are in עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah and we're
picking up at the bottom of דף מ״ב, Daf Mem Bet, עמוד
ב׳. Amud Bet. I want to backtrack a little bit because we're
in the middle of a discussion and maybe it'll help us to
have the whole discussion at once and figure out a little bit
of what's going on. So,
the משנה Mishnah in the middle of מ״ב ע״ב Mem Bet Bet
is saying, המוציא כלים ועליהם צורת חמה צורת לבנה צורת דרקון יוליכם
לים המלח. Hamotze kelim ve’aleihem tzurat chama, tzurat levana, tzurat drakon, yolichem
le'yam hamelach. I know this was reviewed yesterday. This is if we
find something that has the shape of a sun, moon, or a
dragon, we'll take him to ים המלח. Yam Hamelach. And then there
is a discussion about stuff that we find that is עבודה זרה
Avodah Zarah that is מכובד mechubad and stuff that is מבוזה. mevuzeh.
Like stuff that is respectful and stuff that is disgraceful. A whole
interesting thing if somebody is interested in an article about dragons in
the ancient world and in different cultures.
Yeah, it's not the same. Yeah, that's good.
Well, it's not the same but there might be some connections. Really?
Even in China? Could be. Wow. Okay. You're up for this exciting
thing? Okay, yeah.
Did he say it in English or Hebrew? Hebrew. Oh.
So we translate.
All right.
I can translate later, but maybe offline.
I was going to say, you could put it up on the
list.
Send it around. Yes, send it around.
The dragon apparently, according to this one article, and there's probably 500
others, has to do with the serpent. With this and then once
like you know we make that connection then you go, oh, yeah,
of course. So, one and I'm not sure I can put all
the symbolism together and make sense out of them but, you know,
in the time we have, but one thing is that the dragon
has this like up and down, right? Like the slithering motion and
there's something about the slithering motion that is symbolic or represents life,
you know, like a heart monitor kind of thing that goes up
and down.
And then maybe we could take that to the serpent and figure
out how that's related. Where is that life force going to? Is
it idolatrous or is it real? So, I think we have things
here and this is just maybe me trying to make sense out
of it that are
like
too close to something that could be real. We'll see the discussion,
just not, again, not a spoiler, but a heads up where we're
going. We have to ask ourselves stuff that we use, right? Like
stuff that we use in the משכן. Mishkan. Where is the line
between an item that the עובדי כוכבים Ovdei Kochavim is using and
between an item that we're using? And we'll see mention of
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel has these images of the moon in order
to figure out the new month. So, are those idolators if the
משנה Mishnah says you can't have צורת לבנה? tzurat levana? We have
mentioning of צורת לבנה tzurat levana in the תפילות, Tefillot, right? רב
התקין צורת הלבנה. Rav hitkin tzurat halevana. So, like, where are the
lines between items, between items we find, between symbolic things? This is
our project. Guess what?
We're going to begin. We're going to begin. We have a long
discussion and we'll see as much of it as we can cover.
Okay. So, a few lines under this משנה Mishnah on מ״ב ע״ב,
Mem Bet Bet,
רב ששת Rav Sheshet is going to try to put
the משנה Mishnah and the חומרות, chumrot, known חומרות chumrot together. I'm
going to make a quick chart that hopefully will be helpful to
us as we go. So, we
have מותר, mutar, right? Things that are מותר. mutar. And this was
the end of yesterday. Things that are מותר mutar and things that
are אסור. assur. So, of the מזלות, mazalot, of the constellation, everything
is okay except חמה ולבנה, chama u'levana, right? The sun and the
moon. This is according to רב ששת. Rav Sheshet. פרצופים, partzufim,
faces, everything okay except... חוץ מאדם chutz mi-adam
and of the צורות tzorot of the shapes everything except a dragon.
So that now gives us a wide range of things and another
question that this גמרא Gemara is going to ask immediately after רב
ששת Rav Sheshet is trying to distinguish between three, sorry,
three different situations. One is עושה, oseh, so if somebody makes these
things, one is עובד, oved, if somebody worships, and one is
מוצא, motze,
okay, like if somebody finds, right? Because in theory if somebody finds
he should return a lost object, right? But what if that object
is
עבודה זרה?
avoda zara?
Even better, what if it's עבודה זרה avoda zara owned by a
Jew?
All right. We are still on the bottom of מ"ב... mem bet...
מ"ב עמוד ב'. mem bet amud bet. Okay, so after this רב
ששת, Rav Sheshet, אמר מר כל המזלות מותרים חוץ ממזל חמה ולבנה.
Amar mar, kol ha-mazalot mutarin chutz mi-mazal chama u-levana. הכא במאי עסקינן?
Hacha b'mai askinan? אילימא בעושה? Ilima b'oseh? אי בעושה כל המזלות נמי
שרי?
I b'oseh, kol ha-mazalot nami
sharei?
If we say all the מזלות mazalot are allowed except the sun
and the moon, what exactly are we talking about? If we're talking
about somebody that makes all the מזלות, mazalot, all the constellation,
how is this permitted? Because we have a פסוק pasuk in שמות
Shemot כ'... kaf... כ' kaf at the end of יתרו Yitro when
after the, sorry, after the Ten Commandments, the פסוק pasuk tells us
לא תעשון אתי אלהי כסף ואלהי זהב לא תעשו לכם. Lo taasun
iti elohei chesef v'elohei zahav lo taasu lachem. So do not make,
and then there is a strange preposition here, so do not make
something, gods of silver, gods of gold, do not make for you.
This little word there, which we're going to... this is going to
be our פסוק pasuk for the next few discussions, proof, is אתי.
iti. What is אתי? iti? Usually it means with me. So is
it of me? What is it exactly? Okay.
So the understanding here in the גמרא, Gemara, לא תעשון אתי, lo
taasun iti, לא תעשון כדמות שמשי המשמשים לפני במרום. lo taasun kidmut
shamashay ha-meshameshim lefanay bamrom. Don't do things like those figures
of my attendants in the celestial, the celestial beings. Okay. But that
would be obvious, it already says it, לא תעשון, lo taasun, right?
So is that possibly what we're talking about? אלא פשיטא במוצא. Ela
pshita b'motze. Now we're in the option of somebody finding. וכדתנן המוצא
כלים ועליהם צורת חמה צורת לבנה צורת דרקון יוליכם לים המלח.
U'che-datnan ha-motze kelim va-aleihen tzorat
chama tzorat levana tzorat drakon yolichem l'yam ha-melach. So we're
talking about somebody who finds an עבודה זרה. avoda zara. Okay. אי
במוצא אימא מציעתא.
I b'motze eima
metziata.
So now this statement of רב ששת Rav Sheshet has three parts
to it, right? So we will see if those three go together
or if there's places where they need to be separated. כל הפרצופים
מותרים חוץ מפרצוף אדם. Kol ha-partzufim mutarin chutz mi-partzuf adam. אי במוצא
פרצוף אדם מי אסור? I b'motze partzuf adam mi assur? So all
the faces, right, are allowed except for a human face, except for
פרצוף אדם. partzuf adam.
So now in the case where somebody finds an image with the
figure of a human person, then who forbids it? והתנן המוצא כלים
ועליהם צורת חמה צורת לבנה צורת דרקון יוליכם לים המלח. Ve-hatnan ha-motze
kelim va-aleihen tzorat chama tzorat levana tzorat drakon yolichem l'yam ha-melach.
This is what we're saying, right? In the משנה, Mishna, this is
what we just said. If you find a shape of the sun,
the moon, and the dragon, right? צורת דרקון אין פרצוף אדם לא.
Tzorat drakon in partzuf adam lo. This would be implied from this
that the dragon figure has to be... is part of the prohibition
and has to be taken to ים המלח, yam ha-melach, which is
a whole thing to be dealt with because what if I found,
what if I found this עבודה זרה avoda zara in חיפה? Haifa?
Now I have to walk with it all the way to ים
המלח? yam ha-melach? Can't I just throw it in the Mediterranean? Isn't
there a ים המלח yam ha-melach closer? Well, obviously I know the
ים המלח yam ha-melach probably the salt or
chemical
concentration is such that it will destroy it, or right, alter the
shape. But okay. So this statement now leaves us with the idea
that a dragon is included in the prohibition from
the
משנה. Mishna. So let's continue. אלא פשיטא בעושה. Ela Peshita Be'oseh.
So the
one aspect for those who find and one aspect for those who,
one prohibition for those who find and one for those who make.
וכדרב הונא בריה דרב יהושע. Uchederev Huna Berei Derev Yehoshua. אי בעושה
אימא סיפא. Ei Be'oseh Eima Seifa. כל הצורות מותרות חוץ מצורת דרקון.
Kol Hatzurot Mutarot Chutz Mitzurat Drakon. ואי בעושה צורת דרקון מי אסיר?
Ve'ei Be'oseh Tzurat Drakon Mi Assir? והכתיב Vehachtiv back to our פסוק.
Pasuk.
So possibly one way to be reading this would be
the with the regards to one who forms a figure the last
clause of רב ששת Rav Sheshet statement: all the figures are permitted
except the דרקון. Drakon.
Okay and where and where do we find that the דרקון Drakon
is included there is where
it says already or doesn't it say: לא תעשון אתי אלהי כסף
ואלהי מסכה?
Lo Ta'asun Iti Elohei Chesef Ve'elohei
Masecha? הני אין, Hanei In, צורת דרקון Tzurat Drakon לא. Lo.
So
okay so these in these figures only these figures that are mentioned
and again we're checking where is the place of the dragon and
where is the place of the person the that whether we're making
or finding. אלא פשיטא. Ela Peshita. We're not talking about somebody who's
making, this is פשיטא Peshita that it's not allowed from the פסוק.
Pasuk. במוצא, Bemotzei, but we're talking about somebody who finds. וכדתנן המוצא
כלים ועליהם צורת חמה. Uchedetnan Hamotzei Kelim Va'aleihen Tzurat Chama. So this
now excludes the אדם, Adam, the אדם Adam was not in the
משנה Mishnah therefore maybe the אדם Adam for רב ששת Rav Sheshet
is in the מוצא. Motzei. רישא וסיפא במוצא ומציעתא בעושה. Reisha Veseifa
Bemotzei Umtziata Be'oseh. Now try something else. רישא וסיפא במוצא ומציעתא בעושה.
Reisha Veseifa Bemotzei Umtziata Be'oseh.
There's still inconsistency between רב ששת Rav Sheshet and the משנה. Mishnah.
So is it possible that the beginning and the end of the
statement are with somebody who finds and the middle is with somebody
who makes? אמר אביי אין רישא וסיפא במוצא ומציעתא בעושה. Amar Abaye
In Reisha Veseifa Bemotzei Umtziata Be'oseh.
Okay let's see if this if this is going to work. רבא
אמר כולה במוצא ומציעתא רבי יהודה היא.
Rava Amar Kula
Bemotzei Umtziata Rabbi Yehuda Hi. So רבא Rava suggests that the whole
statement of רב ששת Rav Sheshet is referring to somebody who finds,
which is this,
tools or
כלים Kelim
with these figures, and the middle is an opinion of רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda. דתניא רבי יהודה מוסיף אף דמות מניקה וסר אפיס. Detanya
Rabbi Yehuda Mossif Af Dmut Meinika Vesar Apis. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
adds two more figures to these
things the problematic images. דמות מניקה וסר אפיס. Dmut Meinika Vesar Apis.
Who's מניקה? Meinika? מניקה Meinika is a nursing mother. מניקה על שם
חוה שמניקה כל העולם כולו. Meinika Al Shem Chava Shemeinika Kol Ha'olam
Kulo. So this is the the mother that nurses the whole the
whole world. So if you think about it for us the rabbis
call it דמות חוה Dmut Chava but really for the Christians it
would be yes the mother with right
Madonna and child the mother that nurses the whole world. סר אפיס
על שם יוסף ששר ומפיס או מפייס. Sar Apis Al Shem Yosef
She'sar Umepis O Mefayes. He's like a minister and feeding,
מפייס, Mefayes, appeasing like the whole world because he's feeding them during
the time of hunger and this specific figure of
יוסף Yosef ששר ומפיס את
כל העולם כולו She'sar Umepis Et Kol Ha'olam Kulo והוא דנקיט גריווא
וכה כחייל והיא דנקטא בן וכה מניקא. Vehu Denakit Geriva Vecha Kechayal
Vehi Denakta Ben Vecha Meinika. So יוסף Yosef the figure of the
סר אפיס Sar Apis is forbidden only when it is holding
some tools that are like dry measurement גריווא Geriva or measuring with
it, so he looks like he's at work right is there a
picture or something and the mother when she's holding a child and
nursing it.
Yes there's also the picture but it's just the head.
Okay because there was a guy called Sarapis yes that's the same
yes that's the Sarapis. What a Christian you get to a
Christian thing about a mother holding a child possibly.
But that's a reference, and then yeah, that's a reference for the
like
nursing the whole... but like we call חווה אם כל חי, Chava
em kol chai, right, the mother of all living things, and in
other cultures maybe it's not חווה, Chava, it's their mother.
But this
is depicted in a lot of Renaissance images, and you know, yeah,
Steinsaltz
says it might actually be Isis, the Egyptian god, and it also
might be
Dionysus being nursed by
nymphs.
So
it's possible that there's another explanation
besides the Christian one.
I mean,
probably a painful topic, like you know, where is the right the
mother goddess or you know, Mother Earth? I mean, if you think
about it, Adam, but we talk about it in other opportunities. If
in Hebrew with the female form of somebody is like you just
you add "ah", right, ילד ילדה, yeled yalda, סוס סוסה, sus susa,
so Adam goes with אדמה. Adama. So then we have this whole
idea, right, of Mother Earth.
In
fact, he came from the dust of the earth. Oh, right, I
mean literally in in terms of our text.
Right.
But in רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda time, that was not a major
theme in pagan religions. The mother, the mother earth idea, the Greek
and Roman female goddesses were not really like that.
I think just, okay, I mean is what you're saying that there
is Egyptian mother goddesses right, so it's like where did that mother
go to?
Earlier European mother goddesses, but not really not really in Greek.
Well, he has a very descriptive like right that she's holding a
child and is nursing, so she's like the giving mother of the
world.
Okay, is there a Christian reference to the second one?
No, I don't know the Serapis where to put him.
Pagan?
Yeah, where did it go. All right. Okay, so that's that. Now
the דרקון, Drakon, דרקון, Drakon,
which I'm fascinated by it, so I have to say.
Yeah, we need to learn a little more about Egyptian religions which
is probably also...
Wait,
wait,
wait, wait, yes, we're gonna...
we had that whole thing with רבי חייא Rebbe Chiya where we
did incantations so you know, לטעמי חמי L'itamy Chami also. You got
a whole field for us to stop.
Again, not to be a spoiler here, but we will see as
we go through it hopefully that for educational purposes there's certain provisions.
There's permitted either for קירוב Keruv or for education. Right, right. Wikipedia
also identifies Serapis as being originally from Egypt,
which would be interesting with Joseph being in Egypt. All right. Moving
right along, we are on מ"ג ע"א. Mem Gimmel Amud Aleph. תנו
רבנן: Tano rabanan: איזהו צורת דרקון? Ezehu tzorat drakon? פירש Peresh רבי
שמעון בן אלעזר: Rabbi Shimon Ben Elazar: כל שיש לו ציצין בין
פרקיו. Kol she'yesh lo tzitzin bein parakav.
So רש"י Rashi says about it that he has חוליות, chulyot, he
has what are חוליות, chulyot, like in the spine, joints?
Huh?
Like sort of like joints?
No, no, joints.
What are the things on the spine?
Vertebrae. Yeah, vertebrae. So he has and he says ציצין תרגום של
סנפיר, tzitzin targum shel snapir, לשון אחר כמו שערות. lashon acher k'mo
searot. So it's like a between the vertebrae, right, there's like these
spikes. Right, which is very much very much dragony. Crocodile too huh
or not?
No, crocodile doesn't have a thing. I mean I can't draw it
חס וחלילה chas v'chalila but...
oh yeah, the spikes. Okay, little one. לטעמי חמי.
L'itamy Chami. Huh?
לטעמי חמי. L'itamy Chami.
מחוי Machvei רבי אסי Rabbi Assi בין פרקי צוואר. bein pirkei tzavar.
Like he shows that this is... by emotions to show that it's
in the between the joints of the neck. אמר רב חמא בר
רבי חנינא: Amar Rav Chama bar Rabbi Chanina: הלכה כרבי שמעון בן
אלעזר. Halacha k'Rabbi Shimon Ben Elazar. And there's a question that I'm
not sure if I want to go into.
תוספות Tosafot ask what does it what do they mean by הלכה
כרבי שמעון בן אלעזר, Halacha k'Rabbi Shimon Ben Elazar, do you mean
there were other opinions that had something else to say about the
dragon? He says אפילו אם אשכחת תנא דפליג, afilu im ashkechat tana
d'palig, like even if there will be arguments, no, the dragon is
the known with this with this beautiful description of the סנפירים snapirim
in the vertebrae. אמר רבה בר בר חנה, Amar Rabba bar bar
Chana, אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי: Amar Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Levi: פעם
אחת הייתי מהלך אחר רבי אלעזר הקפר Rabbi Elazar Hakapar. בריבי. So
רבה בר בר חנה *Rabba Bar Bar Chana*,
which
is
the one that tells us the fantastic stories
אגדות *aggadot* legends in בבא בתרא *Bava Batra*, so like whenever I
see his name I'm like, hmm, what's coming next? This is going
to be something fantastical. Okay. So he's walking after רבי אלעזר הקפר
Rabbi Elazar Hakapar *Rabbi Elazar HaKappar*, distinguished רבי אלעזר הקפר *Rabbi Elazar
HaKappar* on the way. ומצא שם טבעת taba'at? ועליה צורת דרקון *u'matzah
sham taba'at ve'aleiha tzurat drakon*. He found a ring with a dragon
shape on it. What do we do when we find a lost
object of an עובד כוכבים oved kochavim *oved
kochavim*? ומצא עובד
כוכבים oved kochavim קטן ולא אמר לו כלום *u'matzah oved kochavim katan
ve'lo amar lo klum*. So he finds an underage, right, and עכו"ם
*akum* junior and he doesn't say anything to him. He doesn't say
anything to him. מצא עובד כוכבים oved kochavim גדול ואמר לו בטלה
*matzah oved kochavim gadol ve'amar lo batla*. So now, what is the
problem? The problem is that if I find something that is עבודה
זרה avodah zarah, *avodah zarah*, right, on the ground, if I lift
it up it might be a form of קנין *kinyan*, right, like
הגבהה *hagbahah* and all that. So I can't pick it up but
I want to return it to the right person. No, I want
to throw it away in the ים המלח *Yam HaMelach*. I want
to do something with it, right? So I have to have it
lose the status of עבודה זרה avodah zarah. *avodah zarah* that it
has.
I can't do this. We'll see in a minute that the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* learns from this little incident a number of things. But
this is what happens. He says to the עובד כוכבים oved kochavim
גדול *oved kochavim gadol* revoke the status of it. And he doesn't.
לא בטלה *lo batla*. סטרו ובטלה *setaro u'batla*. So he slapped him
across the face and that's when he revoked the status, the עובד
כוכבים *oved kochavim*.
Wow. Wow.
He was going to do that?
Who's the who's the he?
Slapped the עובד כוכבים *oved kochavim* across the face. Yeah. I don't
know if it was like a you know improv thing.
Fake. Okay. Anyway. שמע מינה תלת *shma mina tlat*. We can learn
from this three things that
yes,
we need for other such מציאות *metzi'ot*. עובד כוכבים מבטל עבודת כוכבים
שלו ושל חברו *oved kochavim mevatel avodat kochavim shelo ve'shel chaveiro*. So
number one, we can get somebody that is an עובד כוכבים *oved
kochavim* that that is not their object to be מבטל *mevatel* the
status of it even if they don't own it.
Yeah. So it actually might matter in this case the Steinsaltz says
he often does, says גוי *goy* does not say specifically עובד כוכבים
*oved kochavim*.
We've had this discussion here.
Well why are you saying? Yeah in this case actually because it
implies that any it doesn't have to actually be an idol worshiper.
It can be anyone who's not Jewish that can
yes. Okay.
Yes. Okay. Leave it. So the first thing שמע מינה *shma mina*
is עובד כוכבים מבטל עבודת כוכבים שלו ושל חברו *oved kochavim mevatel
avodat kochavim shelo ve'shel chaveiro*. So you can a עובד כוכבים *oved
kochavim* can revoke the status of something that is not theirs, right,
that belongs to their friend. Second thing. ושמע מינה יודע בטיב של
עבודת כוכבים ומשמשיה מבטל ושאינו יודע בטיב עבודת כוכבים ומשמשיה אינו מבטל
*u'shma mina yodeia be'tiv shel avodat kochavim u'meshamsheiha mevatel ve'she'eino yodeia be'tiv
avodat kochavim u'meshamsheiha eino mevatel*. So we learn from this encounter with
the junior עכו"ם *akum* and the senior עכו"ם *akum* that the junior
doesn't he knows right that it's idolatrous practices.
No, sorry, if he doesn't know like if he's not of age,
alright, or he maybe doesn't know how to distinguish then he doesn't
have the authority to cancel its status.
And שמע מינה *shma mina* third one. עובד כוכבים מבטל בעל כרחו
*oved kochavim mevatel be'al korcho*. You can force somebody,
right, even if it's against their will you can convince them to
revoke the status of the idol.
So so the second one seems to limit the first one.
The second one
limits yes if you happen to somehow know about the עבודה זרה
Avodah Zarah.
*avodah zarah*
yes then take some
I hear what you're saying. On one hand the
someone that that does not belong to him, right, person B can
cancel for person A but on the other hand he has to
have some knowledge of what this is in order to cancel. Yes.
There's there's a note here about the debate in שולחן Shulchan ערוך
*Shulchan Aruch* and רמב"ם *Rambam* about whether the minor who understands the
nature of idolatry can nullify it or not.
So from the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* it seems not. What do they
say?
Right I'm just saying רמב"ם *Rambam*
paskens no.
Yeah. They need to have some knowledge.
That's that's what. שולחן Shulchan, ערוך *Shulchan Aruch* says it
is
valid but the רמב"ם *Rambam* says no.
Interesting.
Usually רמב"ם *Rambam* also says that. A gentile can nullify
an
object of עבודה זרה avodah zarah, even when it's not his own.
However, the gentile has to be an idol worshiper. So if you
have a gentile who's not, like a Muslim, I presume.
Let's let's not do specifics and let's not do הלכה halacha right
away. Let's just let's just try to go through the text. We
want to learn הלכה! halacha! I know, I know. Cometh nine.
Okay, I
pretend I didn't hear that. Huh? I said I pretend I didn't
hear that.
Which part? Okay. מגדף בר אבי חנינא. Megadef bar avi Chanina. Okay,
so Rabbi Chanina is like whatever, objects.
You say מגדף, megadef, that means really objects, not just like objects.
Yeah, I didn't want to like whatever, translation ridicules. Yeah, he's like
push back. Okay. ולית ליה לרבי אלעזר הקפר ברבי הדתנן V'leit lei
l'rabbi Elazar Hakapar b'ribbi had'tanan like doesn't he know
why does he have to revoke the status? Right, we have another
teaching that we know. המציל מן הארי ומן הדוב ומן הנמר ומן
הגייס Hamatzil min ha'ari umin hadov umin hanamer umin hagais so somebody
that saves something or finds from the lion, the bear, the tiger,
the army forces ומן הנהר umin hannahar the river when it like
goes
the tide goes up and down ומזוטו של ים umizuto shel yam
also ומשלוליתו של נהר umishulito shel nahar the water of a river
והמוצא בסרטיא v'hamotzei b'sartya when somebody finds on the street, on the
way, I don't know if סרטיא sartya street became
a
word thing, פלטיא platyia like the city center, town
center, plaza, thank you, same word, ובכל מקום שהרבים מצויין שם הרי
אלו שלו מפני שהבעלים מתיאשים מהם. uv'chol makom sheharabbim metzuyin sham harei
eilu shelo mipnei shehab'alim mityashim mehem. So we know this from בבא
מציעא, Bava Metzia, right, that if we find something in a place
where the owner is not likely to go back and be able
to find it, then the owners would be מתיאשים mityashim
and then we don't have a problem, like why are we having
a problem? Okay, אמר אביי Amar Abaye ניהי דמן מיאש מאיסורא מי
מיאש. nihi d'min mityaiesh m'isura mi mityaiesh. So this is important. There's
two pieces that this יאוש yeush can have or not have and
look at the statement. מימר אמר אי עובד כוכבים אשכחלה ופלח פלח
לה אי ישראל אשכחלה אידי דדמי יקרין מזבן
לה לעובד כוכבים ופלח לה.
Meimar amar ei oved kochavim ashkechala ufalach palach la ei Yisrael ashkechala
aidi d'damei yakrin mezaben la l'oved kochavim ufalach la. Okay, so yes,
let's say
we need some idolatrous name. Okay, doesn't matter. X, person X has
a ring with an idolatrous image, right, he lost it in the
city center. Okay, so he's מתיאש mityaiesh from finding that particular ring
in that particular city center. However, he's not מתיאש mityaiesh from
the איסור, issur, he's not given up on the fact that this
thing can still be worshiped. It can be worshiped in one of
two ways. If an עובד כוכבים is going to chance across it,
he's going to find it,
then he's just going to take it and worship it because it's
an image. And if a ישראל Yisrael is going to find it,
what is the Jew going to do with it? As גמרא Gemara
doesn't like it.
The Jew, if it's a valuable עבודה זרה, avodah zarah. then he
will sell it to a gentile who then will worship it.
So and that has happened, we used to deal in religious objects
like that.
This is how we gained our
reputation.
But the point is back to רבי אלעזר הקפר. Is it the
goy continuing? This is what yes.
It doesn't mean that's what's really going to happen. That's what the
גמרא.
Gemara
Right, but still this is how things went 1500 years ago.
So
nothing new under the sun. As far as the עובד כוכבים there's
two options. If עובד כוכבים will find it, he'll take it and
worship it. If a Jew will find it, he'll take it sell
it give it to an עובד כוכבים who will worship it. Therefore
he's מתיאש mityaiesh from himself finding his object and taking it back
but he's not מתיאש mityaiesh from the fact that it's going to
be worshiped. And therefore רבי אלעזר הקפר needs to cancel its status
because otherwise it's still an עבודה זרה.
Like there's two things, right, the one thing is the ownership and
one thing is the status.
Okay.
So this is a pushback from if you lose it in a
crowded place you assume יאוש yeush and you assume that that is
ביטול. bitul. Yeah, but
it's not.
Not ביטול. Bitul. It's ביטול Bitul for the ownership, but it's not
ביטול Bitul for the fact that it's עבודה זרה.
So we still need to do the ביטול. Bitul. Alright, challenge, or
not, not challenge but a different case.
תנן, Tnan, התם, Hatam, דמות צורות לבנות Dmut tzorot levanot היו לו
Hayu lo לרבן גמליאל L'Rabban Gamliel בעלייתו B'aliyto בטבלא בכותל B'tavla bakotel
שבהן Shebahen מראה Mareh את ההדיוטות Et hahedyotot ואומר V'omer להם Lahem
כזה ראיתם Kazeh ra'item או כזה ראיתם? O kazeh ra'item? Oh yeah.
Oh yeah. In מסכת Masechet ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, we are told,
yeah, for
the first מצוה Mitzvah given to the Jewish people, first מצוה Mitzvah
given to the Jewish people.
So we, our first משנה, Mishna, our first מצוה, Mitzvah, too many
things, our first מצוה Mitzvah is to, right, establish the calendar and
the new moon. And in order to do that, we need to
know what kind of shape we're seeing in the sky. משנה מפורשת,
Mishna meforeshet, right? We can't
have
צורת לבנה. Tzorat levanah. And here we know that לרבן גמליאל, Rabban
Gamliel, the רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, has in his עלייה, Aliyah, in
his attic, he has a chart, right? So that there's simple people
who don't know what they saw in the sky, they come to
him... sorry, I'm moving from this on something... they come to him,
and it's fine, it's right in the, bit, between.
They come to him and they say, I see, I saw something
like this, I saw something like that, and he has a chart
of the moon and he can say this way or that way.
So challenge, how can he do this, right? ומי שרי? U'mi shari?
Who approved this kind of thing to him, to have images of
the moon?
Well, he was the נשיא. Nasi.
Coming up. And what does it imply that he was the נשיא?
Nasi? Not so much that like oh, he was the נשיא, Nasi,
but you'll see that it means that there were people coming to
him and it's not like he could worship it.
I just realized the connection between שרי, Shari, right, permitted, and לאשר
L'asher in Hebrew, like to allow. I don't know if they're related
but I liked it. Okay, לא תעשון אתי, Lo ta'asun iti, לא
תעשון כדמות שמשי המשמשים לפני. Lo ta'asun kidmut shamashay ham'shamshim lefanay. Okay.
So now exactly the פסוק Pasuk we brought earlier from שמות, Shemot,
don't make the שמשים Shamashim that are serving me. How are we
gonna deal with it? אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, לא אסרה תורה אלא
שמשים שאפשר לעשות כמותן. Lo asra Torah ela shamashim she'efshar la'asot k'motan.
So
we're
going to see that the rabbis divide the heavens into things we
don't quite exactly understand of what they call שמשין של מטה Shamashin
shel mata and שמשין של מעלה. Shamashin shel ma'ala.
We're in the realm that is going to be hard to explain,
right? Because if God is one, how can there be attendants to
the oneness? And how can there be attendants to the oneness on
high and on low? And also in עשרת הדברות, Aseret Hadibrot, right,
it's going to say to us, and we'll see this פסוק, Pasuk,
לא תעשה לך פסל וכל תמונה אשר בשמים ממעל, Lo ta'aseh lecha
pesel v'chol tmunah asher bashamayim mima'al, so in the heaven above, אשר
בארץ מתחת Asher ba'aretz mita'at ואשר במים מתחת לארץ. Va'asher bamayim mita'at
la'aretz. So that there's like a lot of layers to
whatever
wherever is we live, and in there's different שמשים. Shamashim אביי Abaye
says, לא אסרה תורה Lo asra Torah אלא Ela שמשים Shamashim. שאפשר
לעשות כמותן. She'efshar la'asot k'motan. So he's trying now to respond to
this issue with רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and separate it, and let's
see if he succeeds.
כדתניא, K'tanya, לא יעשה אדם Lo ya'aseh adam בית Bayit תבנית Tavnit
היכל, Heichal, אכסדרה Achsadra תבנית Tavnit אולם, Ulam, חצר Chatzer תבנית Tavnit
עזרה, Azara, שולחן Shulchan תבנית Tavnit שולחן, Shulchan, מנורה Menorah תבנית Tavnit
מנורה. Menorah. But, pause for a minute. A person may not construct
a house that looks exactly like the משכן, Mishkan, can you imagine?
A patio or a balcony, right, that is in the shape of
the entrance hall, the חצר Chatzer courtyard that looks like the temple
courtyard, a שולחן that looks like a שולחן, a מנורה Menorah that
looks like a מנורה. Menorah. But,
and if you're starting to think of challenges to this, the גמרא
Gemara will challenge it too. So just a second, we'll go through
the discussion here. אבל Aval הוא עושה Hu oseh של חמש Shel
chamesh ושל שש V'shel shesh ושל שמונה, V'shel shmoneh, ושל שבע לא
יעשה. V'shel sheva lo ya'aseh.
So he can make a מנורה Menorah of five branches, of six,
of eight, and of seven he shouldn't do. Yes, Charlie?
I think I saw the same
ברייתא Baraita in מנחות.
Menachot. The התניא *ha'tanya* appears in מנחות *Menachot*. What's that התניא *ha'tanya*?
Okay. אפילו של שאר מיני
מתכות
*afilu shel shear minei matachot*. See the back about the מנורה *menorah*.
It says, "don't make the
מנורה *menorah* זהב טהור *zahav tahor*." So they say in a ברייתא
baraita. *braita*, not even if it's not gold, don't make it. So
questions... okay, leave it. רבי יוסי בר יהודה *Rabbi Yosi Bar Yehuda*
אומר אף של עץ לא יעשה כדרך שעשו בית חשמונאי *omer af
shel etz lo ya'aseh kederech she'asu beit Chashmonai*. So יוסי בר יהודה
*Yosi Bar Yehuda* says, don't make a מנורה *menorah* of wood like
the חשמונאים *Chashmonaim* did. And there's questions that are just to mention,
but beyond the scope of our time now,
of
how
do we understand the instructions for the מנורה *menorah*? Like is it
limiting or including or excluding? So I'm just mentioning, but I'm not
going there. So now about the חשמונאים *Chashmonaim*, they say, אמרו לו
משם ראיה *amru lo misham ra'aya*? This is where you get your
proof? שפודים של ברזל היו וחופים בבעץ העשירו עשאום של כסף חזרו
והעשירו עשאום של זהב *shipudim shel barzel hayu vechofim beva'atz heshiru asaum
shel kesef chazru ve'heshiru asaum shel zahav*. So they had,
during
the time of the חשמונאים *Chashmonaim*, they made their מנורה *menorah* from
ברזל *barzel*, from iron, and then they covered it with tin. When
they got richer, they made it out of silver, and then when
they got richer more, they made it of gold. ושמשים שאי אפשר
לעשות כמותם *v'shamashim she-ee efshar la'asot kemotam*... רגע *rega*... now
all this, all this is not possible in the case of the
moon, right? Because these are שמשים shamashin של מטה *shamashim shel mata*,
and the moon is שמש של מעלה *shamash shel ma'ala*.
So what's the prohibition... רגע רגע רגע רגע *rega rega rega
rega*...
we have,
look, we clearly have a problem. Yeah. We have all this and
we have רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel, *Rabban Gamliel* having images of the
moon in his attic, which publicly, right? Everybody knows about it. So
now we're trying to figure out where can we find allowance for
this with all the texts we have available, right? So the first
thing we're saying is maybe we're only talking about שמשים shamashin? *shamashim*
in the lower thing, not to do something like this. ושמשים שאי
אפשר לעשות כמותם מי שרי *v'shamashim she-ee efshar la'asot kemotam mi shari*?
והתניא veha tanya, לא תעשון אתי iti? *vehatanya lo taasun iti*. Back
to our פסוק pasuk *pasuk* from the beginning of this discussion, לא
תעשון כדמות שמשיי המשמשים לפניי במרום *lo taasun kidmut shamashay ham'shamshim l'fanay
bamarom*. How,
or as a question,
"you shall not make
with me these gods of silver and of gold," maybe this is
taught, "you should not make
these,
the figures of my שמשים shamashin *shamashim*, also on high," right?
How do we get that it's only in the תחתון *tachton*?
Okay. אמר אביי Amar Abaye, *amar Abaye*,
we
are at the top of מג ב *Mem-Gimel Bet*, לא אסרה תורה
Torah אלא בדמות ארבע פנים בהדי הדדי *lo asra Torah ela bidmut
arba panim bahadi hadadi*. There's four... there's figures of four faces that
are not allowed. This is from the chariots, from the chariots mentioned
in Ezekiel.
Lion,
eagle, who's the second? I forgot already. Ox. Ox and human. Thank
you, the שור *shor*, ox and human. If we say this, לא
אסרה תורה Torah אלא בדמות *lo asra Torah ela bidmut*, only these
four faces,
then according to that, it would mean that the sun and the
moon are allowed. That would be a problem, right? אלא מעתה פרצוף
אדם לחודא דשתרי *ela me'ata partzuf adam l'chuda deshtari*?
So then we can say this would mean a difficulty, right? Because
now the face of a person is permitted. אלמא תניא כל הפרצופים
מותרים חוץ מפרצוף אדם *alma tanya kol hapartzufim mutarim chutz mi'partzuf adam*.
But why then is it taught that all the faces are permitted
except for a human face? And then we have this contradiction. אמר
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda בריה דרב יהושע *amar Rav Yehuda breih d'Rav
Yehoshua*, מפרקי דרבי יהושע שמיע לי *mi'pirkei d'Rabbi Yehoshua shamia li*. רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda,
*Rav Yehuda* said, the son of רב Rav יהושע *Rav Yehoshua*, teach
me from... or...
I
heard... I heard a lecture from the teachings of רבי יהושע *Rabbi
Yehoshua*, לא תעשון *lo taasun*. אתי, iti. לא תעשון אותי. lo sa'asun
osi. So this is when I said in the beginning we have
a strange preposition there. Do not make, what is אתי? Like with
me? But maybe it means אותי, osi, me. Don't make me, אבל
שאר שמשים שרי. aval she'ar shamashin shari. So what does it mean
don't make me? Who's in the image of God?
Person, people. So don't make, make
in
the face of a human is forbidden, but others, other שמשים
of God might be permitted. ושאר שמשים מי שרי Ushe'ar shamashin mi
shari according to this would be permitted. Question. And is it permitted
to do the other שמשים? והתניא, Veha tanya, back to this פסוק
in שמות. Shemot. לא תעשון אתי לא תעשון כדמות שמשיי המשמשים לפני
במרום כגון אופנים ושרפים וחיות הקודש ומלאכי השרת. lo sa'asun iti lo
sa'asun kidmut shamashay hameshamshim lefanay bamarom kegon ofanim veserafim vechayot hakodesh umalachei
hasharet. Right,
it's
taught in another place, in another ברייתא. baraita Don't make these gods
with me, אתי. Don't make the the like attendants that are with
me, namely those on high, the
אופנים ושרפים וחיות הקודש ofanim veserafim vechayot hakodesh like all the whatever
ministering angels on high. אמר אביי, Abaye לא אסרה תורה אלא שמשים
שבמדור עליון. lo asra Torah ela shamashin shebimdor elyon. So Abaye's response
is, okay, the Torah forbids
the figures that are שמשים in the upper heavens, in the high,
okay. ושבמדור תחתון מי שרי? Veshebimdor tachton mi shari? So who permits
the lower places? We're still, we're still like trying
to find where, where is it? This is none of this, this
is not going to be the answer for רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel
so we'll get out of it.
והתניא, Veha tanya אשר בשמים לרבות חמה ולבנה כוכבים ומזלות ממעל לרבות
מלאכי השרת. asher bashamayim lerabot chama ulevana kochavim umazalot mima'al lerabot malachei
hasharet. If it says בשמים
bashamayim in the Ten Commandments, there should be
including everything in the heaven.
Okay, but then we have שמים ממעל shamayim mima'al and it would
imply the מדור תחתון mador tachton as well. כי תניא ההיא
לעובדם. Ki tanya hahi le'ovdam.
So this now, back to the discussion we had in the beginning.
Are we talking about making? Are we talking about worshipping? Are we
talking about finding? And the answer here is כי תניא ההיא לעובדם.
ki tanya hahi le'ovdam. This ברייתא Baraisa that talks about these ministering
angels and all that is when the situation is to worship them.
There's no prohibition to form, but there is a prohibition to worship,
right? This is what it says in the עשרת הדברות. Aseret Hadibrot.
אי לעובדם אפילו שלשול קטן נמי. I le'ovdam afilu shilshul katan nami.
This is very cute. If we're talking about worship, we can't worship
anything, even שלשול קטן. shilshul katan. שלשול קטן shilshul katan is a
tiny little worm.
You get kids pulling them out of the ground in the winter
after they come out of the mud.
There's probably some worm somewhere.
We still call them שלשול shilshul in in modern Israel. Yeah, my
kids. Okay. אי הכי נמי ומסיפא דקרא נפקא דתניא אשר בארץ לרבות
ימים ונהרות הרים וגבעות מתחת לרבות שלשול קטן. I hachi nami umiseifa
dekra nafka detanya asher ba'aretz lerabot yamim uneharot harim ugeva'ot mitachat lerabot
shilshul katan.
So if we're talking about worship, nothing is allowed to be worshipped,
even the tiniest worm, the seas, the rivers, the mountains, the hills,
everything that is underneath,
including the tiniest little worm. ועשייה גרידתא מי שרי? Ve'asiya geridta mi
shari?
So back to the problem with רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel who has
these figures. Like who allowed him to make it? Got it. Can't
worship. We dealt with some of the finding, right? If we find
we have to cancel the status, right? In order to take it
or dispose of it in an appropriate way. Now what about the
making? והתניא again, לא תעשון אתי לא תעשון כדמות שמשיי המשמשים לפני
במרום כגון חמה ולבנה כוכבים ומזלות. lo sa'asun iti lo sa'asun kidmut
shamashay hameshamshim lefanay bamarom kegon chama ulevana kochavim umazalot. שאני רבן גמליאל
דאחרים עשו לו.
Shani Rabban Gamliel
de'acherim asu lo.
So the solution what אביי proposed earlier is is rejected.
So now we have the difficulty still with רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel,
and what is one way that we can solve it? We're not
allowed to make... any of these things, right, any of these images?
And but for רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel he's not allowed to make
it, somebody else made it for him, which will allow him to
have it. So this is very interesting, I think it's very interesting.
So making not, worshipping not, finding we have a way to dispose
of it, owning
is
okay. If he didn't make it, if he doesn't worship it, owning
seems to be having an okay; there's no prohibition
about
somebody owning them. So I can keep my dragons. Okay. והא רב
יהודה דאחרים עשו לו? Veha Rav Yehuda de'achirim asu lo? ואמר לו
שמואל לרב יהודה, Ve'amar lo Shmuel l'Rav Yehuda, שיננא. Shinnana. Okay,
now there is a case of רב יהודה Rav Yehuda where others
made for him some sort of a figure and שמואל Shmuel said
to רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda שיננא, Shinnana, שיננא Shinnana from שיניים, shinnayim,
yes,
from being sharp, biting, biting on stuff.
Destroy this one's eyes, right? סמי עיניה דדין. Sami einei d'din. Like
if you disfigure the idolatrous image, it would lose some of its
idolatrous status and then it won't
be better to own something that's not a complete one. I'm not
sure
how to make it all work. Okay. התם בחותמו בולט ומשום חשדא.
Hatam bechotamo bolet umishum chashda. So the seal that
רב יהודה has is like a ring, and the ring, in order
to make a stamp,
the image is sticking out, right, so that when you stamp it
it can be engraved?
Okay, so that's why because it's בולט bolet you can break something
in
it and bas-relief,
it's in relief, right?
Is that what the word is?
What do you mean relief?
When it comes out,
it stands out from the background.
It's just a phrase in
English with בולט, bolet,
בולט, bolet, yeah, the ring is בולט. bolet. Okay. Okay. דתניא טבעת
שחותמה בולט אסור להניחה ומותר לחתום בה. Detanya taba'at shechotama bolet assur
lehannichah umutar lachtom bah.
So you can't carry it on the finger because that would be
like carrying an עבודה זרה, but you can seal with it. חותמה
שוקע מותר להניחה ואסור לחתום בה.
Chotama shokei'a mutar lehannichah
ve'assur lachtom
bah. ומי חייש שיננא לחשדא? Umi chaish Shinnana lechashda? Were we
concerned about this, the טבעת? והא בי כנישתא דשף ויתיב בנהרדעא. Veha
bei knishta d'shaf v'yativ beneharde'a.
There was a synagogue, a בית כנסת beit knesset that was destroyed
in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and then was יתיב, yativ, was re-established
again in נהרדעא, Neharde'a, דאוקימי ביה אנדרטא. D'ukimei bei andarta.
This is very fascinating, don't you think? We had a synagogue somewhere,
and it was destroyed for some reason, and then rebuilt miles and
miles away,
and in modern Hebrew actually אנדרטא andarta is like a memorial, right?
So it's like some statue was erected in it of a king
or something. והוו עיילי ביה אבוה דשמואל ולוי ומצלו בגויה ולא חיישי
לחשדא. Vahavu ayeli bei avu d'Shmuel v'Levi umatzlu beigau velo chaishi lechashda.
And still, like all these people, right, שמואל Shmuel and לוי Levi
would
go and pray in it, מצלו, matzlu, and they were not worried
about the fact that there is this אנדרטא. andarta. So what does
the גמרא answer to that? רבים שאני. Rabbim shani. This is a
public situation, so now a whole different aspect is being introduced into
this עבודה זרה. How public is our activity? So
now remember, we're still dealing with רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel? and his
moon images in his attic. So how does that help us? How
does this synagogue situation, which is a public place, how does that
help us for רבן גמליאל? Rabban Gamliel והא רבן גמליאל דיחיד הוה.
Veha Rabban Gamliel dyachid hava. He was an individual, right, so how
does that help? כיון דנשיא הוא שכיחי רבים גביה ואיבעית אימא דפרקים
הוה. Keivan deNasi hu shchichi rabbim gabei ve'iba'it eima deperakim hava. So
this is what Charlie, Charlie, right, you said this earlier? Oh, he
was the נשיא. Nasi. Not in the sense that he was a
נשיא Nasi that he has special whatever provisions, right, that he can
allow himself, but that yes, he's alone, but lots of people come
to see
him. And
also that if you if you look for some
alternative then the the figures that he had were not complete like
the רב יהודה that says break it a little bit they had
פרקים perakim they had pieces okay so the complete figures are forbidden
one way to look at it ואי בעית אימא להילמד שאני דתניא
V'ee bayis ayma lehilamed shani d'tanya לא לא תלמד לעשות אבל אתה
למד להבין ולהורות
Lo lo tilmad
la'asot aval ata lamed lehavin ulehorot so לא תלמד
לעשות lo tilmad la'asot so and
if still if still there is you're looking for another answer about
the situation of רבן גמליאל להילמד שאני דתניא lehilamed shani d'tanya in
order to when it comes to education to teach oneself or others
then the then it's different and we have a quote from דברים
Devarim לא תלמד לעשות lo tilmad la'asot
you will not like learn to do but from the fact that
it says לא תלמד לעשות lo tilmad la'asot
right to do it excludes all the other things that you can
learn for and therefore the גמרא says אבל אתה למד להבין ולהורות
aval ata lamed lehavin ulehorot so you may learn in order to
understand or to teach it to others and רבן גמליאל'ס Rabban Gamliel's
situation you can
he could use the לבנה levana in order to teach others and
that was the way to go around having an image in his
in his attic I I really think it's fascinating like it deserves
much greater attention and and unpacking that idea that certain things are
permitted for the sake of תורה study that normally would be forbidden
normally you would say to somebody and קל וחומר kal vachomer a
great רב no you can't have specifically any of these images that
the משנה'ס Mishnah's saying and
powerful
to me that for the sake of תורה study we make certain
allowances that otherwise we would say no and it
can
be carried further alright a little more
we're picking up another piece from the משנה Mishnah from our משנה
Mishnah of מ"ב עמוד ב Mem Bais Amud Bais there רבי שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel was saying שעל המכובדים אסורים שעל
המבוזין מותרים she'al hamichubadim asurim she'al hamevuzin mutarim he distinguished between
עכו"ם כלים Akum kelim that are respectable and things that are disgraceful
okay מבוזים mevuzim so which which is which אמר רב מכובדים למעלה
מן המים מבוזים למטה מן המים ושמואל אמר אלו ואלו מבוזין הן
אלו ואלו הן מכובדים
Amar Rav michubadim lemala min hamayim mevuzim lemata min hamayim uShmuel amar
elu ve'elu mevuzin hen
elu ve'elu hen michubadim okay רגע שנייה rega shniya let's leave the
מכובדים michubadim
so some people say it's not the vessel itself it's not the
item itself but where it is okay the location should be above
the water above the level of the water whether not sure if
it's a cup or a
okay or whether it is under the water under the
where there's food so I guess like where things get
mucky it's whatever disrespectful and where things are respectful above the food
the muck then yes okay
and שמואל Shmuel said both of these אלו ואלו elu ve'elu
when it comes to eating eating utensils they're not respectful but the
כבוד kavod comes from location how we wear them okay so we
have שירים shirin על שירים ועל הנזמים ועל הטבעות al shirin ve'al
hanezanim ve'al hataba'ot so that
things
that are on bracelets
nose rings and
rings תניא כוותיה דשמואל מכובדים שעל השירים ועל הנזמים
ועל הטבעות מבוזים שעל היורות ועל הקומקמסין ועל מחמי חמין ועל הסדינים
ועל המטפחות Tanya k'vasei d'Shmuel michubadim she'al hashirin ve'al hanezanim ve'al hataba'ot
mevuzim she'al hayurot ve'al hakumkumsin ve'al machamei chamin ve'al hasadinim ve'al hamitpachot
so there's a ברייתא that agrees with שמואל Shmuel the מכובדים michubadim
are on the bracelets and nose rings and the טבעות taba'ot the
rings and the ones that are not respectable are on יורות yurot
we saw the יורה yora the cooking the pots
and קומקום kumkum is still a kettle in Israel modern times ומחמי
חמין. v'chamay machamay chamin. Okay, quick משנה *Mishna* and then discuss it
tomorrow. רבי יוסי אומר שוחק וזורה לרוח או מטיל לים אמרו לו
אף הוא נעשה
זבל שנאמר לא ידבק בידך מאומה מן החרם *Rabbi Yose omer shochek
v'zoreh laruach o metil layam amru lo af hu na'aseh zevel she'ne'emar
lo yidbak b'yadcha m'uma min hacharem*. I would just introduce and maybe
it's a good place to pause and continue tomorrow. רבי יוסי *Rabbi
Yose* says
when one encounters
an idol and an idolatrous figure, he can שוחק וזורה לרוח *shochek
v'zoreh laruach*, you can grind it and toss it to the wind,
או מטיל לים *o metil layam*, cast it to the ocean. That's
what you asked earlier if you have to go to an earlier
sea than the Dead Sea if you find your עבודה זרה *avodah
zarah*
in
the north. So there is an issue because if we grind it,
that might mix with whatever זבל *zevel*, with manure, with compost, and
then this could benefit the Jew and by default, the Jew would
benefit from עבודה זרה *avodah zarah*. No eye-rolling. One, it says לא
ידבק בידך מאומה מן החרם *lo yidbak b'yadcha m'uma min hacharem*, you
should like nothing should cling to you. But think about it as,
whatever, spiritual germs, right? If there was like, let's say, a radioactive
something, I'm in a field I know nothing about, right? But if
there was something, whatever, we wouldn't say, "Hey, it's just a tiny
little thing, let's just toss it in the river." Right? Even a
tiny little thing would be bad. So this is at least how
they viewed it. And we'll see a whole discussion that compares the
Golden Calf and משה *Moshe* grinding and letting the people drink and
treating those water like the סוטה *sotah* drinking water to
enlighten us and tell us about the people who's into עבודה זרה
*avodah zarah* and who's not into the עבודה זרה *avodah zarah*. With
that, we conclude. A great day to everybody. Thank you for being
with us and, yeah.
I'm subbing for dragons.
Now dream about it.
And my article had a lot of pictures, but it was just
printed with nothing. Do you have your two-state thing? Yes,
they're
just
not in use anymore. This is the flag of the Chinese Empire.
Not in use anymore?
Right, they, when they became a republic, they got rid of all
the imperial...
Look, look at this. This is like all the different names of
snakes. Oh wow. And then how, where would the dragons go in
different cultures?
No, for
us, נחש, פתן, תנין, צפע, שפיפון, שרף, בהמות, נחש עקלתון, לויתן נחש
עקלתון, לויתן נחש בריח *nachash, peten, tanin, tsefa, shfifon, saraf,
behemoth, nachash akalaton, levyatan nachash
akalaton, levyatan nachash
bariach*.
Holy crap, they're in...
they're in school. I had this whole question because we didn't discuss
in the gallery, images of faces, human faces, you know, we accepted
in photographs. Okay, I will find out, an email today about the,
I'm
not aware of...
I think there's more problems like which I'm sorry I didn't mention.
There's greater problems because like we have ancient synagogues from that era
with the constellation and like we have בית כנסת *beit knesset* in
בית אלפא *Beit Alfa* in עמק יזרעאל *Emek Yizre'el* that has גלגל
המזלות *galgal hamazalot* on it. So is it a matter of making,
worshipping, finding and owning is not a problem? And what does making
constitute in modern times with photography, right? Is it only a making
of a 3D thing that's protruding and all that, or is it
flat? What are we going to do with 3D printing?
I don't
know.
I'm not, I'm just,
I'm done.
Okay. So I, so they, I actually had a class to teach
on פורים *Purim* and I balked and said I'm taking the day
off. רבי לינסברגר *Rabbi Linzburger* joined today and he sent an email
to the course thread
that says we're canceling class. Apparently I wasn't the only one.
And then some back and forth about what happens to the Jew.
Yeah, you get a break. I'm enjoying it.
Yeah,
you shut
down, you shut down everything.
Wow.